so now that we have seen that unrolling
can really help both reduce the overall
work and also schedule the work better
we might be tempted to do unrolling all
the time so is there any downside to
unrolling well yes there is so first
there is code bloat let's say that our
original loop body was four instructions
after we unroll for example it might be
that instructions 1 through 3 need to be
replicated and this is for example or
branch so we can just have one so now
there is fewer instructions executed per
original iteration we had four per
iteration now we have seven per 2
iterations but the code size is much
larger here we had four instructions in
our code now we have seven instructions
in our code if we decide to unroll more
than once meaning do the work of let's
say four of these iterations the code
size will be proportionally larger so
the code grows quickly with the number
of unrolling we do second what if the
number of iterations is unknown at the
beginning for example this could be a
while loop in that case here we do one
iteration at a time here we are doing
two iterations at a time what if we
needed to exit here even in a for loop
where we know the number of iterations
in advance what if the number of
iterations we need is not a multiple of
n the number of iterations we are doing
per iteration of the loop so we might
still for example we might need to do
seven iterations of this loop we unroll
it once now we need to do this three
times and then exit in the middle so how
do we handle this the solutions to these
problems do exist but they are beyond
the scope of this class so these are
questions that are better answered in an
advanced compiler class not in an
architecture class